<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Database xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pubseed.theseed.org/FIG/Html/ERDBtk_DBD.xsd">
  <Title>Cancer Treatment Database</Title>
  <Notes>This database contains information relating to treatments
  for different medical conditions. The goal is to determine the conditions under
  which certain treatments are effective. For each Source (which may be a cell line
  or a human patient), we record treatment events and measurement events. The measurements
  could be gene-expression data or observed symptoms. We wish eventually to correlate
  treatment effectiveness with the measurements prior to treatment.</Notes>
  <Regions/>
  <Diagram height="800" width="800" ratio="0.7" size="90"
      fontSize="11" editable="0" />
  <Entities>
    <Entity name="Drug" keyType="string" default="id">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" row="7" col="7" />
      <Notes>A drug is a compound used in treatments, for example [b]picoplatin[/i].
      The ID is the name of the drug.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="description" type="long-string">
          <Notes>text describing the drug, often a URL to a web site</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Treatment" keyType="string" default="id">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" row="5" col="7" />
      <Notes>A treatment is a therapeutic regimen, normally a set of drugs,
      dosages, and dosage intervals. The ID is a unique but meaningful name.
      For example, distinct FOLFOX treatments (varying dosages or intervals)
      must be given precise names like [i]FOLFOX-1[/i] and [i]FOLFOX-2[/i].</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="description" type="text">
          <Notes>text describing the treatment, often a URL to an appropriate
          web site</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Source" keyType="short-string" default="id type">
      <DisplayInfo theme="red" row="5" col="3" />
      <Notes>A source of DNA or RNA. It can be an actual patient or a cell line. The
      ID is a unique code string.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="type" type="short-string">
          <Notes>the type of source-- [i]patient[/i] or [i]cell line[/i]</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="gender" type="char">
          <Notes>the gender of the source-- [b]M[/b] (male), [b]F[/b] (female) or space (not known or relevant)</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="age" type="int">
          <Notes>the age of the source in years, or 0 if it is not known or relevant</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Study" keyType="string" default="id">
      <DisplayInfo theme="navy" row="3" col="5" />
      <Notes>A study involves giving treatments to a set of sources and
      gathering expression-values to determine what happened.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="description" type="text">
          <Notes>full description of the study</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Probe" keyType="short-string" default="id">
      <DisplayInfo theme="green" row="5" col="1" />
      <Notes>A probe used to find DNA on a microarray. The ID is a unique code string.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="sequence" type="long-string">
          <Notes>the DNA sequence associated with the probe</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Event" keyType="counter" default="id type-event">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" row="5" col="5" />
      <Notes>An event is a measurement or a treatment relevant to a single source. The
      events are organized in chronological order so the effects of a treatment can be
      seen in context. The ID is a sequence number assigned when the record is inserted.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="type-event" type="char">
          <Notes>the type of event-- [b]M[/b] for a measurement or [b]T[/b] for a treatment</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Measurement" keyType="counter" default="id type-measurement">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" row="7" col="3" />
      <Notes>A measurement is information about the state of a source. It could be a textual
      assertion by a physician or it could be microarray expression data. A measurement is always
      associated with exactly one event, and the event contains the time of the measurement and relates
      it to the source. The measurement ID is the same as the parent event ID.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="type-measurement" type="char">
          <Notes>the type of measurement-- [b]P[/b] for a physician assertion, [b]M[/b] for microarray
          expression data</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="measurement" type="text">
          <Notes>text of the measurement; this could be string-encoded microarray data or the text of the physician
          assertion</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
    <Entity name="Classifier" keyType="short-string" default="id type-class">
      <DisplayInfo theme="green" row="3" col="1" />
      <Notes>A classifier is a procedure for determining the condition of a source, with an eye to
      deciding whether the source will respond to specific treatments. The ID is a unique code assigned
      by the creator.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="type-class" type="short-string">
          <Notes>a code string indicating the class which a source belongs to if the classifier is
          satisfied</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="description" type="text">
          <Notes>a text description of what the classification means</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="rule" type="long-string">
          <Notes>a JSON string representing a list of lists, essentially the condition in conjunctive normal form</Notes>
          <Asides>The classifier connects to a set of probes which are ordinally numbered. Each sub-list in the condition
          is a list of 2-tuples, one per probe, that represents the allowable range for the probe's values. The sub-list is
          satisfied if all the probe expression values are within the ranges. The classifier is satisfied if at least one
          sub-list is satisfied.</Asides>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Entity>
  </Entities>
  <Relationships>
    <Relationship name="Study2Source" arity="1M" from="Study" to="Source"
        converse="Source2Study" embedded="1">
        <DisplayInfo theme="navy" caption="Study to\nSource" />
        <Notes>This relationship connects a study to the sources (patients and cell lines)
        used in the study. A source is unique to a study. A single patient involved in two
        studies will appear twice in the database.</Notes>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Drug2Treatment" arity="MM" from="Drug" to="Treatment"
        converse="Treatment2Drug">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" caption="Treatment\nto Drug" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects a drug to a treatment in which it participates,
      and contains information about how the drug is used in the treatment. Provision
      is made for the possibility that the drug is not given in constant dosages at
      regular intervals.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="dosage" type="float">
          <Notes>the mean dosage, in milligrams</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="frequency" type="float">
          <Notes>the mean dosage frequency, in doses per day</Notes>
        </Field>
        <Field name="description" type="text">
          <Notes>a detailed description of how the drug is given, in what amounts,
          and how often</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Study2Treatment" arity="MM" from="Study" to="Treatment"
        converse="Treatment2Study">
      <DisplayInfo theme="navy" caption="Study to\nTreatment" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects a study to the types of treatments used in the study.</Notes>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Source2Event" arity="1M" from="Source" to="Event"
        converse="Event2Source" embedded="1">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" caption="Source to\nEvent" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects an event to the single source to which the event applies.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="timestamp" type="date">
          <Notes>the date and time of the event; for a treatment, this is the date and
          time of the first dose.</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
      <FromIndex>
        <Notes>This index presents the events in the chronological order in which they occurred to the source.</Notes>
        <IndexFields>
          <IndexField name="timestamp" order="ascending" />
        </IndexFields>
      </FromIndex>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Event2Treatment" arity="MM" from="Event" to="Treatment"
        converse="Treatment2Event">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" caption="Event to\nTreatment" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects a treatment event to the treatment applied.</Notes>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Event2Measurement" arity="1M" from="Event" to="Measurement"
        converse="Measurement2Event" embedded="1">
      <DisplayInfo theme="blue" caption="Event to\nMeasurement" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects a measurement to the single event that contains the
      time of measurement and links it to the measured source. Every measurement has one
      associated event, but not all events may connect to measurements.</Notes>
    </Relationship>
    <Relationship name="Classifier2Probe" arity="MM" from="Classifier" to="Probe"
        converse="Probe2Classifier">
      <DisplayInfo theme="green" caption="Classifier\nto Probe" />
      <Notes>This relationship connects a classifier to the probes interrogated by the classification
      function.</Notes>
      <Fields>
        <Field name="ordinal" type="int">
          <Notes>ordinal position of the probe in the classifier's function</Notes>
        </Field>
      </Fields>
      <FromIndex>
        <Notes>This index presents the probes for a classifier in ordinal sequence.</Notes>
        <IndexFields>
          <IndexField name="ordinal" order="ascending" />
        </IndexFields>
      </FromIndex>
    </Relationship>
  </Relationships>
</Database>