<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Database xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pubseed.theseed.org/FIG/Html/ERDBtk_DBD.xsd">
    <Title>PATRIC Bioinformatics Database</Title>
    <Notes>The PATRIC database contains large tables describing the characteristics
        of over one hundred thousand genomes.
    </Notes>
    <Regions>
    </Regions>
    <Diagram height="800" width="800" ratio="0.7" size="90"
        fontSize="12" editable="0" />
    <Entities>
        <Entity name="Genome" keyType="short-string" default="id name">
            <DisplayInfo theme="red">
                <RegionInfo name="" col="4" row="3" />
            </DisplayInfo>
            <Notes>A genome represents a specific organism with DNA, or a
                specific meta-genome. All DNA sequences in the database belong to
                genomes. This table can be listed using p3-all-genomes. You
                can also access data from genome records given a list of genome
                IDs using p3-get-genome-data.
            </Notes>
        </Entity>
        <Entity name="Contig" keyType="string" default="id length">
            <DisplayInfo theme="red">
                <RegionInfo name="" col="2" row="3" />
            </DisplayInfo>
            <Notes>A contig is a contiguous sequence of base pairs belonging to
                a single genome. The key of the contig is the genome ID followed
                by a colon and then the contig ID.
            </Notes>
        </Entity>
        <Entity name="Feature" keyType="string" default="id">
            <DisplayInfo theme="green">
                <RegionInfo name="" col="4" row="5" />
            </DisplayInfo>
            <Notes>A feature (sometimes also called a gene) is a part of a
                genome that is of special interest. Features may be spread across
                multiple DNA sequences (contigs) of a genome, but never across more
                than one genome. Each feature in the database has a unique FIG
                ID that functions as its ID in this table. Given a list of feature
                IDs, the feature data can be accessed using p3-get-feature-data.
            </Notes>
        </Entity>
        <Entity name="Drug" keyType="short-string" default="id name">
            <DisplayInfo theme="blue">
                <RegionInfo name="" col="6" row="3" />
            </DisplayInfo>
            <Notes>A drug represents an antibiotic or other anti-microbial therapeutic
            compound. Drugs are the anchor for resistance and susceptibility information
            regarding genomes in the database. This table can be listed using
            p3-all-drugs.
            </Notes>
        </Entity>
        <Entity name="Family" keyType="short-string" default="id">
            <DisplayInfo theme="green" caption="Family">
                <RegionInfo name="" col="4" row="7" />
            </DisplayInfo>
            <Notes>A (protein) family contains a set of proteins that perform the same function.
            Given a list of family IDs, the family data can be accessed using p3-get-family-data.</Notes>
        </Entity>
    </Entities>
    <Relationships>
        <Relationship name="GenomeDrug" from="Genome" to="Drug" arity="MM" converse="DrugGenome">
            <DisplayInfo theme="blue" caption="Genome\nDrug" />
            <Notes>This relationship connects a genome to a drug and contains the resistance/susceptiblity
            data for the genome/drug pair. It is navigated from a list of genomes using p3-get-genome-drug-data and
            from a list of drugs using p3-get-drug-genome-data.</Notes>
        </Relationship>
        <Relationship name="GenomeContig" from="Genome" to="Contig" arity="1M" embedded="1"
            converse="ContigGenome">
            <DisplayInfo theme="red" caption="Contig\nGenome" />
            <Notes>This relationship connects a genome to its DNA sequences. It is navigated by
            p3-get-genome-contigs proceeding from a list of genomes to contig data.</Notes>
        </Relationship>
        <Relationship name="GenomeFeature" from="Genome" to="Feature" arity="1M" embedded="1"
            converse="FeatureGenome">
            <DisplayInfo theme="green" caption="Genome\nFeature" />
            <Notes>This relationship connects a genome to its constituent features. It is navigated
            by p3-get-genome-features proceeding from a list of genomes to feature data.</Notes>
        </Relationship>
        <Relationship name="FamilyFeature" from="Family" to="Feature" arity="1M" converse="FeatureFamily"
            embedded="1">
            <DisplayInfo theme="green" caption="Feature\nFamily" />
            <Notes>This relationship connects protein families to features. It is navigated by p3-get-family-features
            from a list of family IDs to features. The family IDs are stored as attributes of the feature record
            for navigation from features to the families.</Notes>
        </Relationship>
    </Relationships>
</Database>
